And the color she loved to wear so much was possibly the only thing that was truly about her, the one thing she had agency over, because like most other women of her generation in India, she'd never been allowed to exist beyond what was dictated by custom and tradition. She'd been married at 17, and after 65 years of marriage, when my grandfather died suddenly one day, her loss was unbearable. But that day, she was going to lose something else as well, the one joy she had: to wear color. In India, according to custom, when a Hindu woman becomes a widow, all she's allowed to wear is white from the day of the death of her husband. No one made my grandmother wear white. However, every woman she'd known who had outlived her husband, including her mother, had done it. This oppression was so internalized, so deep-rooted, that she herself refused a choice. She passed away this year, and until the day she died, she continued to wear only white. I have a photograph with her from earlier, happier times. In it, you can't really see what she's wearing -- the photo is in black and white. However, from the way she's smiling in it, you just know she's wearing color. This is also what fashion can do. It has the power to fill us with joy, the joy of freedom to choose for ourselves how we want to look, how we want to live -- a freedom worth fighting for. And fighting for freedom, protest, comes in many forms. Widows in India like my grandmother, thousands of them, live in a city called Vrindavan. And so, it's been a sea of white for centuries. However, only as recently as 2013, the widows of Vrindavan have started to celebrate Holi, the Indian festival of color, which they are prohibited from participating in. On this one day in March, these women take the traditional colored powder of the festival and color each other. With every handful of the powder they throw into the air, their white saris slowly start to suffuse with color. And they don't stop until they're completely covered in every hue of the rainbow that's forbidden to them. The color washes off the next day, however, for that moment in time, it's their beautiful disruption. This disruption, any kind of dissonance, can be the first gauntlet we throw down in a battle against oppression. And fashion -- it can create visual disruption for us -- on us, literally. Lessons of defiance have always been taught by fashion's great revolutionaries: its designers. Jean Paul Gaultier taught us that women can be kings. Thom Browne -- he taught us that men can wear heels. And Alexander McQueen, in his spring 1999 show, had two giant robotic arms in the middle of his runway. And as the model, Shalom Harlow began to spin in between them, these two giant arms -- furtively at first and then furiously, began to spray color onto her. McQueen, thus, before he took his own life, taught us that this body of ours is a canvas, a canvas we get to paint however we want. Somebody who loved this world of fashion was Karar Nushi. He was a student and actor from Iraq. He loved his vibrant, eclectic clothes. However, he soon started receiving death threats for how he looked. He remained unfazed. He remained fabulous, until July 2017, when Karar was discovered dead on a busy street in Baghdad. He'd been kidnapped. He'd been tortured. And eyewitnesses say that his body showed multiple wounds. Stab wounds. Two thousand miles away in Peshawar, Pakistani transgender activist Alisha was shot multiple times in May 2016. She was taken to the hospital, but because she dressed in women's clothing, she was refused access to either the men's or the women's wards. What we choose to wear can sometimes be literally life and death. And even in death, we sometimes don't get to choose. Alisha died that day and then was buried as a man. What kind of world is this? Well, it's one in which it's natural to be afraid, to be frightened of this surveillance, this violence against our bodies and what we wear on them. However, the greater fear is that once we surrender, blend in and begin to disappear one after the other, the more normal this false conformity will look, the less shocking this oppression will feel. For the children we are raising, the injustice of today could become the ordinary of tomorrow. They'll get used to this, and they, too, might begin to see anything different as dirty, something to be hated, something to be extinguished, like lights to be put out, one by one, until darkness becomes a way of life. However, if I today, then you tomorrow, maybe even more of us someday, if we embrace our right to look like ourselves, then in the world that's been violently whitewashed, we will become the pinpricks of color pushing through, much like those widows of Vrindavan. How then, with so many of us, will the crosshairs of a gun be able to pick out Karar, Malala, Alisha? Can they kill us all? The time is now to stand up, to stand out. Where sameness is safeness, with something as simple as what we wear, we can draw every eye to ourselves to say that there are differences in this world, and there always will be. Get used to it. And this we can say without a single word. Fashion can give us a language for dissent. It can give us courage. Fashion can let us literally wear our courage on our sleeves. So wear it. Wear it like armor. Wear it because it matters. And wear it because you matter. Thank you. (Applause)
Y el color que tanto le gustaba usar era quizá lo único que la identificaba de verdad, lo único que podía decidir, porque al igual que la mayoría de las mujeres de su generación en India nunca había tenido la oportunidad de existir fuera de los cánones impuestos por la costumbre y la tradición. Se había casado a los 17, y luego de 65 años de matrimonio, cuando un día mi abuelo murió inesperadamente, esa pérdida le resultó insoportable. Pero ese día perdería algo más; su única alegría: usar ropa de colores. Según la tradición india, cuando una mujer queda viuda, el único color que puede usar es el blanco desde el momento en que fallece su esposo. Nadie la obligó a vestir de blanco. Sin embargo, todas las mujeres que conocía y que habían sobrevivido a sus maridos, incluyendo a su propia madre, lo habían hecho. Esta opresión estaba tan internalizada, tan arraigada, que hasta ella misma se negó a elegir. Falleció este año, y hasta el día de su muerte siguió usando exclusivamente el color blanco. Conservo una foto suya de años anteriores, más felices. Allí no se ven los colores que usa. Es una foto en blanco y negro. Pero, a juzgar por su sonrisa, se deduce que su ropa es de colores. Esta es otra cosa que la moda puede hacer. Tiene el poder de llenarnos de alegría. la alegría de poder elegir libremente y por nosotros mismos cómo vestirnos, cómo queremos vivir. Es una libertad por la que vale la pena luchar. Y en esa lucha por la libertad, la protesta adopta diversas formas. Las viudas como mi abuela de la India viven, junto a otras miles, en una ciudad llamada Vrindavan. Desde hace siglos, las viudas conforman allí un verdadero mar blanco. Sin embargo, recién en el año 2013, las viudas de Vrindavan han empezado a celebrar el "Holi", el festival de color de la India, donde les estaba prohibido participar. En este único día de marzo, las mujeres se arrojan polvos de colores, que es la tradición del festival. Con cada puñado de polvo que arrojan al aire, sus saris blancos empiezan lentamente a cubrirse de colores. Y no se detienen hasta estar completamente cubiertas con las tonalidades de un arco iris que les está prohibido. El color desaparece al día siguiente, pero, al menos por una vez, son parte de una bella disrupción. Esta disrupción, y cualquier otra disonancia, puede ser la primera chispa en la batalla contra la opresión. Y la moda puede representar un quiebre en la estética visual en nosotros, literalmente. Los grandes revolucionarios de la moda son los diseñadores que siempre han hecho demostraciones de verdadera rebeldía: Jean Paul Gaultier nos enseñó que las mujeres pueden ser reyes. Thom Browne nos enseñó que los hombres pueden usar tacones. Y Alexander McQueen, en la presentación de su colección de primavera en 1999, instaló dos enormes brazos robotizados en medio de la pasarela, y mientras la modelo Shalom Harlow giraba entre ellos, estos dos robots, tímidamente al principio y luego con furia empezaron a rociarla con pintura de color. De este modo, McQueen nos enseñó -—antes de quitarse la vida— que nuestro cuerpo es un lienzo que podemos pintar del modo que nos plazca. A quien le encantaba este mundo de la moda era a Karar Nushi. Era un estudiante y actor iraquí. Le fascinaba la ropa llamativa, ecléctica. Pero empezó a recibir amenazas de muerte por la forma en que se vestía. No se inmutó. Siguió siendo fabuloso, hasta que en julio de 2017 fue encontrado muerto en una concurrida calle de Bagdad. Lo habían secuestrado. Lo habían torturado. Un testigo dijo que el cuerpo presentaba múltiples heridas. Heridas de arma blanca. A 3200 km de Peshawar, Alisha, activista transexual pakistaní, recibió múltiples disparos en mayo de 2016. Fue trasladada al hospital pero como vestía ropa de mujer se le negó el acceso al pabellón masculino y también al femenino. La ropa que decidimos usar puede significar, literalmente, la diferencia entre la vida y la muerte. Y a veces, ni siquiera podemos decidir sobre nuestra muerte. Alisha murió ese día y fue sepultada como un hombre. ¿En qué mundo vivimos? Pues bien, uno en el que sentir temor es natural; temor a esta vigilancia, a esta violencia contra el cuerpo y la manera en que nos vestimos. Sin embargo, el gran temor es que si nos rendimos, si no nos diferenciamos y empezamos a desaparecer uno atrás de otro, más normal parecerá esta falsa aceptación, menos asfixiante nos resultará esta opresión. Por los niños que estamos criando, la injusticia de hoy puede ser lo común de mañana. Se acostumbrarán, y ellos también pueden llegar a creer que lo distinto es sucio, digno de ser odiado, suprimido, como luces que se apagan, una a una, hasta que la oscuridad se transforma en un modo de vida. Pero si hoy yo, mañana Uds. y quizá muchos otros algún día defendemos el derecho de vestirnos como deseamos, en un mundo que ha sido violentamente privado de color, y seremos ese rayo de color que abre una luz en el camino, como las viudas de Vrindavan. ¿Cómo es posible entonces que siendo tantos nosotros la mira de un armapueda apuntar a Karar, a Malala, a Alisha? ¿Pueden matarnos a todos? Es hora de ponerse de pie, de salir del montón. En un mundo donde la uniformidad brinda seguridad, con algo tan simple como la ropa podemos hacer que los ojos ajenos se posen en nosotros para decir que en este mundo hay diferencias y que siempre las habrá. Acostumbrémonos a eso. Y esto se puede decir sin pronunciar una sola palabra. La moda puede ser un lenguaje de disenso. Nos puede dar valor. La moda es, literalmente, la oportunidad de ponernos el traje de la valentía. Usémoslo. Usémoslo como armadura. Usémoslo porque es importante. Y usémoslo porque Uds. son importantes. Gracias. (Aplausos)